Flies. Chapter 4. Painted faces and long hair. The first rhythm that they became
used to was the slow swing from dawn to quick dusk. They accepted the pleasures
of morning, the bright sun, the welming sea, and sweet air, as a time when play
was good, and life so full that hope was not necessary, and therefore forgotten.
Toward noon, as the floods of light fell more nearly to the perpendicular, the
stark colors of the morning were smoothed in pearl and opolescence, and
the heat, as though the impending sun's height gave it momentum, became a blow
that they ducked, running to the shade and lying there, perhaps even sleeping.
Strange things happened at midday. The glittering sea rose up, moved apart in
plains of blatant impossibility. The coral reef and the few stunted palms
that clung to the more elevated parts would float up into the sky, would
quiver, be plucked apart, run like raindrops on a wire, or be repeated as
in an odd succession of mirrors.
Sometimes land loomed where there was no land, and flicked out like a bubble as
the children watched. Piki discounted all this learnedly as a mirage. And
since no boy could reach even the reef over the stretch of water where the
snapping sharks waited, they grew accustomed to these mysteries and
ignored them just as they ignored the miraculous throbbing stars. At midday
the illusions merged into the sky, and there the sun gazed down like an angry
eye. Then at the end of the afternoon, the mirage subsided, and the horizon
became level and blew and clipped as the sun declined. That was another time of
comparative coolness, but menaced by the coming of the dark. When the sun sank,
darkness dropped on the island like an extinguisher, and soon the shelters were
full of restlessness under the remote stars. Nevertheless, the northern
European tradition of work, play, and food right through the day, made it
possible for them to adjust themselves wholly to this new rhythm. The little
and persal had early crawled into a shelter, and stayed there for two days,
talking, singing, and crying, till they thought him bad, and were faintly
amused. Ever since then he had been peaked, redeyed, and miserable, a little
who played little, and cried often. The smaller boys were known now by the
generic title of Littleims. The decrease in size from Ralph Down was gradual, and
though there was a dubious region inhabited by Simon and Robert and
Maurice, nevertheless no one had any difficulty in recognizing biggin at one
end and Littlelands at the other. The undoubted little, those aged about six,
led a quite distinct and at the same time intense life of their own. They ate
most of the day, picking fruit where they could reach it, and not particular
about ripess and quality. They were used now to stomach aches and a sort of
chronic diarrhea. They suffered untold terrors in the dark and huddled together
for comfort. Apart from food and sleep, they found time for play, aimless and
trivial, in the white sand by the bright water. They cried for their mothers much
less often than might have been expected. They were very brown and
filthully dirty. They obeyed the summons of the conchk, partly because Ralph blew
it, and he was big enough to be a link with the adult world of authority, and
partly because they enjoyed the entertainment of the assemblies, but
otherwise they seldom bothered with the bigans, and their passionately emotional
and corporate life was their own. They had built castles in the sand at the bar
of the little river. These castles were about 1 ft high and were decorated with
shells, withered flowers, and interesting stones. Round the castles
was a complex of marks, tracks, walls, railway lines that were of significance
only if inspected with the eye at beach level. The little ones played here, if
not happily, at least with absorbed attention, and often as many as three of
them would play the same game together.
Three were playing here now. Henry was the biggest of them. He was also a
distant relative of that other boy whose malberry marked face had not been seen
since the evening of the great fire. But he was not old enough to understand
this, and if he had been told that the other boy had gone home in an aircraft,
he would have accepted the statement without fuss or disbelief. Henry was a bit of a leader
this afternoon, because the other two were Perl and Johnny, the smallest boys
on the island. Perl was mousecoled and had not been very attractive even to his
mother. Johnny was well-built, with fair hair and a natural belligerance. Just
now he was being obedient because he was interested, and the three children
kneeling in the sand were at peace.
Roger and Maurice came out of the forest. They were relieved from duty at
the fire and had come down for a swim.
Roger led the way straight through the castles, kicking them over, burying the
flowers, scattering the chosen stones.
Maurice followed, laughing, and added to the destruction. The three little ends
paused in their game and looked up. As it happened, the particular marks in
which they were interested had not been touched, so they made no protest. Only
Perl began to whimper with an eyeful of sand, and Maurice hurried away. In his
other life, Maurice had received chastisement for filling a younger eye
with sand. Now, though there was no parent to let fall a heavy hand, Maurice
still felt the unease of wrongdoing. At the back of his mind formed the
uncertain outlines of an excuse. He muttered something about a swim and
broke into a trot. Roger remained, watching the little. He was not
noticeably darker than when he had dropped in, but the shock of black hair
down his nape and low on his forehead seemed to suit his gloomy face, and made
what had seemed at first an unsociable remoteness into something forbidden
forbidding. Perl finished his whimper and went on playing, for the tears had
washed the sand away. Johnny watched him with China blue eyes, then began to
fling up sand in a shower, and presently Perl was crying again. When Henry tired
of his play and wandered off along the beach, Roger followed him, keeping
beneath the palms and drifting casually in the same direction. Henry walked at a
distance from the palms in the shade because he was too young to keep himself
out of the sun. He went down the beach and busied himself at the water's edge.
The great Pacific tide was coming in, and every few seconds the relatively
still water of the lagoon heaved forwards an inch. There were creatures
that lived in this last fling of the sea, tiny transparencies that came
questing in with the water over the hot, dry sand, with impalpable organs of
scents. They examined this new field.
Perhaps food had appeared, where at the last incursion there had been none. Bird
droppings, insects, perhaps any of this strewn to try of landward life. Like a
myriad of tiny teeth and a saw, the transparencies came scavenging over the
beach. This was fascinating to Henry. He poked about with a bit of stick that
itself was waveworn and whitened and evagrant and tried to control the
motions of the scavengers. He made little runs that the tide filled and
tried to crowd them with creatures. He became absorbed beyond mere happiness as
he felt himself exercising control over living things. He talked to them, urging
them, ordering them. Driven back by the tide, his footprints became bays in
which they were trapped and gave him the illusion of mastery. He squatted on his
hands at the water's edge, bowed with a shock of hair falling over his forehead
and past his eyes, and the afternoon sun emptied down invisible arrows. Roger
waited, too. At first he had hidden behind a great palm, but Henry's
absorption with the transparencies was so obvious that at last he stood out in
full view. He looked along the beach.
Perl had gone off crying, and Johnny was left in triumphant possession of the
castles. He sat there, crewing to himself and throwing sand at an
imaginary Perl. Beyond him, Roger could see the platform and the glints of spray
where Ralph and Simon and Piggy and Maurice were diving in the pool. He
listened carefully, but could only just hear them. A sudden breeze shook the
fringe of palm trees so that the fronds tossed and fluttered. 60 ft above Roger,
several nuts, fibrous lumps as big as rugby balls, were loosed from their
stems. They fell about him with a series of hard thumps, and he was not touched.
Roger did not consider his escape, but looked from the nuts to Henry and back
again. The subs soil beneath the palm trees was a raised beach, and
generations of palms had worked loose in this the stones that had lain on the
sands of another shore. Roger stooped, picked up a stone, aimed, and threw it
at Henry. Threw it to miss. The stone, that token of preposterous time, bounced
5 yards to Henry's right, and fell in the water. Roger gathered a handful of
stones, and began to throw them. Yet there was a space round Henry, perhaps
six yards in diameter, into which he dare not throw. Here, invisible yet
strong, was the taboo of the old life.
Round the squatting child was the protection of parents and school and
policemen and the law. Roger's arm was conditioned by a civilization that knew
nothing of him and was in ruins. Henry was surprised by the plopping sounds in
the water. He abandoned the noiseless transparencies and pointed at the center
of the spreading rings like a setter.
This side and that the stones fell, and Henry turned obediently, but always too
late to see the stones in the air. At last he saw one and laughed, looking for
the friend who was teasing him. But Roger had whipped behind the palm again,
was leaning against it, breathing quickly, his eyelids fluttering. Then
Henry lost interest in stones, and wandered off. Roger. Jack was standing
under a tree about 10 yards away. When Roger opened his eyes and saw him, a
darker shadow crept beneath the sworthiness of his skin, but Jack noticed nothing. He was eager,
impatient, beckoning so that Roger went to him. There was a small pool at the
end of the river, damned back by sand and full of white waterlies and
needle-like reads. Here Sam and Eric were waiting and Bill. Jack, concealed
from the sun, knelt by the pool and opened the two large leaves that he
carried. One of them contained white clay and the other red. By them lay a
stick of charcoal brought down from the fire. Jack explained to Roger as he
worked. They don't smell me. They see me, I think. Something pink under the
trees. He smeared on the clay. If only I'd. He turned a half-concealed face up
to Roger and answered the incomprehension of his gaze. For hunting, like in the war, you know,
dazzle paint like things trying to look like something else. he twisted in the
urgency of telling. Like moths on a tree trunk. Roger understood and nodded
gravely. The twins moved toward Jack and began to protest timidly about
something. Jack waved them away. Shut up. He rubbed the charcoal stick between
the patches of red and white on his face. No, you two come with me. He ped
his reflection and disliked it. He bent down, took up a double handful of
lukewarm water, and rubbed the mess from his face. Freckles and sandy eyebrows
appeared. Roger smiled unwillingly. You don't half look a mess. Jack planned his
new face. He made one cheek and one eye socket white. Then he rubbed red over
the other half of his face and slashed a black bar of charcoal across from right
ear to left jaw. He looked in the pool for his reflection, but his breathing
troubled the mirror. Sam Eric, get me a coconut, an empty one. He knelt, holding
the shell of water. A rounded patch of sunlight fell on his face, and a
brightness appeared in the depths of the water. He looked in astonishment, no
longer at himself, but at an awesome stranger. He split the water and leapt
to his feet, laughing excitedly. Beside the pool, his sinnowy body held up a
mask that drew their eyes and appalled them. He began to dance, and his
laughter became a bloodthirsty snarling.
He capered toward Bill, and the mask was a thing on its own, behind which Jack
hid, liberated from shame and self-consciousness. The face of red and
white and black swung through the air and jigged toward Bill. Bill started up
laughing. Then suddenly he fell silent and blundered away through the bushes.
Jack rushed toward the twins. "The rest are making a line. Come on, but we Come
on, I'll creep up and stab. The mask compelled them. Ralph climbed out of the bathing
pool and trotted up the beach and sat in the shade beneath the palms. His fair
hair was plastered over his eyebrows, and he pushed it back. Simon was
floating in the water and kicking with his feet, and Maurice was practicing
diving. Piggy was mooning about, aimlessly, picking up things and
discarding them. The rockpools, which so fascinated him, were covered by the
tide, so he was without an interest until the tide went back. Presently,
seeing Ralph under the palms, he came and sat by him. Piggy wore the
remainders of a pair of shorts. His fat body was golden brown, and the glasses
still flashed when he looked at anything. He was the only boy on the
island whose hair never seemed to grow.
The rest were shockheaded. But Piggy's hair still lay in wisps over his head, as though
baldness were his natural state, and this imperfect covering would soon go
like the velvet on a young stag's antlers. I've been thinking, he said,
about a clock. We could make a sundial.
We could put a stick in the sand. And then the effort to express the
mathematical processes involved was too great. He made a few passes instead.
"And an airplane and a TV set," said Ralph sourly. "And a steam engine."
Piggy shook his head. "You have to have a lot of metal things for that," he
said. "And we haven't got no metal, but we got a stick." Ralph turned and smiled
involuntarily. Piggy was a boar. His fat, his asthma, and his matterof fact
ideas were dull. But there was always a little pleasure to be got out of pulling
his leg, even if one did it by accident.
Piggy saw the smile and misinterpreted it as friendliness. There had grown up
tacitly among the biggin the opinion that Piggy was an outsider, not only by
accent, which did not matter, but by fat and asthma and specs, and a certain
disincclination for manual labor. Now, finding that something he had said made
Ralph smile, he rejoiced and pressed his advantage. We got a lot of sticks. We
could have a sund dial each, then we should know what the time was. A fat lot
of good that would be. You said you wanted things done so as we could be
rescued. Oh, shut up. He leapt to his feet and trotted back to the pool just
as Maurice did a rather poor dive. Ralph was glad of a chance to change the
subject. He shouted as Maurice came to the surface. Belly flop. Belly flop.
Maurice flashed a smile at Ralph who slid easily into the water. Of all the
boys, he was the most at home there. But today, irked by the mention of rescue,
the useless footling mention of rescue.
Even the green depths of water and the shattered golden sun held no balm.
Instead of remaining and playing, he swam with steady strokes under Simon and
crawled out of the other side of the pool to lie there, sleek and streaming
like a seal. Piggy, always clumsy, stood up and came to stand by him. So that
Ralph rolled on his stomach and pretended not to see. The mirages had
died away and gloomily he ran his eye along the taut blue line of the horizon.
The next moment he was on his feet and shouting, "Smoke! Smoke!" Simon tried to
sit up in the water and got a mouthful.
Maurice, who had been standing ready to dive, swayed back on his heels, made a
bolt for the platform, then swerved back to the grass under the palms. There he
started to pull on his tattered shorts to be ready for anything. Ralph stood,
one hand holding back his hair, the other clenched. Simon was climbing out
of the water. Piggy was rubbing his glasses on his shorts and squinting at
the sea. Marica got both legs through one leg of his shorts. Of all the boys,
only Ralph was still. "I can't see no smoke," said Piggy incredulously. "I
can't see no smoke, Ralph. Where is it?"
Ralph said nothing. Now, both his hands were clenched over his forehead so that
the fair was kept out of his eyes. He was leaning forward, and already the
salt was whitening his body. "Ralph, where's the ship?" Simon stood by,
looking from Ralph to the horizon.
Maurice's trousers gave way with a sigh, and he abandoned them as a wreck, rushed
toward the forest, and then came back again. The smoke was a tight little knot
on the horizon, and was uncoiling slowly. Beneath the smoke was a dot that
might be a funnel. Ralph's face was pale as he spoke to himself. They'll see our
smoke. Piggy was looking in the right direction now. It don't look much. He
turned round and peered up at the mountain. Ralph continued to watch the
ship ravenously. Color was coming back into his face. Simon stood by him,
silent. I know I can't see very much, said Piggy. But have we got any smoke?
Ralph moved impatiently, still watching the ship. The smoke on the mountain.
Maurice came running and stared out to see. Both Simon and Piggy were looking
up at the mountain. Piggy screwed up his face, but Simon cried out as though he
had heard himself. Ralph.
Ralph. The quality of his speech twisted Ralph on the sand. You tell me, said
Piggy anxiously. Is there a signal?
Ralph looked back at the dispersing smoke in the horizon, then up at the
mountain. Ralph, please, is there a signal? Ralph put out his hand timidly
to touch Ralph, but Ralph started to run, splashing through the shallow end
of the bathing pool, across the hot white sand and under the palms. A moment
later, he was battling with the complex undergrowth that was already engulfing
the scar. Simon ran after him, then Maurice. Piggy shouted, "Ralph, please,
Ralph!" Then he too started to run, stumbling over Maurice's discarded
shorts before he was across the terrace.
Behind the four boys, the smoke moved gently along the horizon, and on the
beach, Henry and Johnny were throwing sand at Perl, who was crying quietly
again. and all three were in complete ignorance of the excitement. By the time
Ralph had reached the land out of the scar, he was using precious breath to
swear. He did desperate violence to his naked body among the grasping creepers,
so that blood was sliding over him. Just where the steep ascent of the mountain
began, he stopped. Maurice was only a few yards behind him. Piggy specks,
shouted Ralph. If the fire's all out, we'll need them. He stopped shouting and
swayed on his feet. Piggy was only just visible, bumbling up from the beach.
Ralph looked at the horizon than up to the mountain. Was it better to fetch
Piggy's glasses, or would the ship have gone? or if they climbed on. Supposing
the fire was all out and they had to watch Piggy crawling nearer and the ship
sinking under the horizon. Balanced on a high peak of need, agonized by
indecision, Ralph cried out, "Oh God, oh God!" Simon, struggling with the bushes,
caught his breath. His face was twisted.
Ralph blundered on, savaging himself as the wisp of smoke moved on. The fire was
dead. They saw that straight away. Saw what they had really known down on the
beach when the smoke of home had beckoned. The fire was out, smokeless
and dead. The watchers were gone. A pile of unused fuel lay ready. Ralph turned
to the sea. The horizon stretched impersonal once more, barren of all but
the faintest trace of smoke. Ralph ran stumbling along the rocks, saved himself
on the edge of the pink cliff, and screamed at the ship, "Come back! Come
back!" He ran backwards and forwards along the cliff, his face always to the
sea, and his voice rose insanely, "Come back! Come back!" Simon and Maurice
arrived. Ralph looked at them with unwinking eyes. Simon turned away,
smearing the water from his cheeks.
Ralph reached inside himself for the worst word he knew. They let the bloody
fire go out. He looked down the unfriendly side of the mountain. Piggy
arrived out of breath and whimpering like a little. Ralph clenched his fist
and went very red. The intentness of his gaze, the bitterness of his voice
pointed for him. "There they are." A procession had appeared far down among
the pink stones that lay near the water's edge. Some of the boys wore
black caps, but otherwise they were almost naked. They lifted sticks in the
air together whenever they came to an easy patch. They were chanting something
to do with the bundle that the errant twins carried so carefully. Ralph picked
out Jack easily, even at that distance, tall, red-haired, and inevitably leading
the procession. Simon looked now from Ralph to Jack, as he had looked from
Ralph to the horizon, and what he saw seemed to make him afraid. Ralph said
nothing more, but waited while the procession came nearer. The chant was
audible, but at that distance, still wordless. Behind Jack walked the twins,
carrying a great stake on their shoulders. The gutted carcass of a pig
swung from the stake, swinging heavily as the twins toiled over the uneven
ground. The pig's head hung down with gaping neck and seemed to search for
something on the ground. At last, the words of the chant floated up to them
across the bowl of blackened wooden ashes. Kill the pig, cut her throat,
spill her blood. Yet, as the words became audible, the procession reached
the steepest part of the mountain, and in a minute or two, the chant had died
away. Piggy sniveled, and Simon shushed him quickly, as though he had spoken too
loudly in church. Jack, his face smeared with clays, reached the top first and
hailed Ralph excitedly with lifted spear. Look, we've killed a pig. We
stole up on them. We got in a circle.
Voices broke in from the hunters. We got in a circle. We crept up. The pigs
squealled. The twins stood with the pig swinging between them, dropping black
gouts on the rock. They seemed to share one wide, ecstatic grin. Jack had too
many things to tell Ralph at once.
Instead, he danced a step or two, then remembered his dignity and stood still,
grinning. He noticed blood on his hands and grimaced distastefully. but for
something on which to clean them, then wiped them on his shorts and laughed.
Ralph spoke. "You let the fire go out." Jack checked, vaguely irritated by
this irrelevance, but too happy to let it worry him. "We can light the fire
again." "You should have been with us, Ralph. We had a smashing time. The twins
got knocked over. We hit the pig. I fell on top. I cut the pig's throat," said
Jack proudly, and yet twitched as he said it. "Can I borrow yours, Ralph, to
make a nick in the hilt?" The boys chattered and danced. The twins
continued to grin. There was lashings of blood, said Jack, laughing and
shuddering. You should have seen it.
We'll go hunting every day. Ralph spoke again horsely. He had not moved. You let
the fire go out. This repetition made Jack uneasy. He looked at the twins and
then back at Ralph. We had to have him in the hunt, he said, or there wouldn't
have been enough for a ring. He flushed, conscious of a fault. The fire's only
been out an hour or two. We can light up again. He noticed Ralph's scarred
nakedness and the somber silence of all four of them. He sought charitable in
his happiness to include them in the thing that had happened. His mind was
crowded with memories. Memories of the knowledge that had come to them when
they closed in on the struggling pig.
Knowledge that they had outwitted a living thing, imposed their will upon
it. Taken away its life like a long satisfying drink. He spread his arms
wide. You should have seen the blood.
The hunters were more silent now, but at this they buzzed again. Ralph flung back
his hair. One arm pointed at the empty horizon. His voice was loud and savage
and struck them into silence. There was a ship. Jack, faced at once with too
many awful implications, ducked away from them. He laid a hand on the pig and
drew his knife. Ralph brought his arm down, fist clenched, and his voice
shook. There was a ship out there. You said you'd keep the fire going, and you
let it out. He took a step toward Jack, who turned and faced him. They might
have seen us. We might have gone home.
This was too bitter for Piggy, who forgot his timidity and the agony of his
loss. He began to cry out shrilly. You and your blood, Jack Meridu. You and
your hunting. We might have gone home.
Ralph pushed Piggy to one side. I was chief and you were going to do what I
said. You talk, but you can't even build huts. Then you go off hunting and let
out the fire. He turned away, silent for a moment. Then his voice came again on a
peak of feeling. There was a ship. One of the smaller hunters began to wail.
The dismal truth was filtering through to everybody. Jack went very red as he
hacked and pulled at the pig. The job was too much. We needed everyone. Ralph
turned. You could have had everyone when the shelters were finished, but you had
to hunt. We needed meat. Jack stood up as he said this, the bloodied knife in
his hand. The two boys faced each other.
There was the brilliant world of hunting, tactics, fierce exhilaration,
skill, and there was the world of longing and baffled common sense. Jack
transferred the knife to his left hand and smudged blood over his forehead as
he pushed down the plastered hair. Piggy began again. You did not have let that
fire out. You said you'd keep the smoke going. this from Piggy and the whales of
agreement from some of the hunters drove Jack to violence. The bolting look came
into his blue eyes. He took a step and able at last to hit someone, stuck his
fist into Piggy's stomach. Piggy sat down with a grunt. Jack stood over him.
His voice was vicious with humiliation.
You would, would you, Fatty? Ralph made a step forward and Jack smacked Piggy's
head. Piggy's glasses flew off and tinkled on the rocks. Piggy cried out in
terror, "My specks!" He went crouching and feeling over the rocks, but Simon,
who got there first, found them for him.
Passions beat about Simon on the mountaintop with awful wings. One side's
broken. Piggy grabbed and put on the glasses. He looked malevolently at Jack.
I got to have them specks. Now I only got one eye. Just you wait. Jack made a
move toward Piggy, who scrambled away till a great rock lay between them. He
thrust his head over the top and glared at Jack through his one flashing glass.
Now I only got one eye. Just you wait.
Jack mimicked the wine and scrambled.
Just you wait. Yeah. Piggy and the parody were so funny that the hunters
began to laugh. Jack felt encouraged. He went on scrambling and the laughter rose
to a gale of hysteria. Unwillingly, Ralph felt his lips twitch. He was angry
with himself for giving way. He muttered. That was a dirty trick. Jack
broke out of his girration and stood facing Ralph. His words came in a shout.
All right. All right. He looked at Piggy at the hunters at Ralph. I'm sorry about
the fire. I mean, there I He drew himself up. I apologize.
The buzz from the hunters was one of admiration at this handsome behavior.
Clearly they were of the opinion that Jack had done the decent thing, had put
himself in the right by his generous apology, and Ralph obscurely in the
wrong. They waited for an appropriately decent answer. Yet Ralph's throat
refused to pass one. He resented, as an addition to Jack's misbehavior, this
verbal trick. The fire was dead. The ship was gone. Could they not
see? Anger instead of decency passed his throat. That was a dirty trick. They
were silent on the mountaintop, while the opaque look appeared in Jack's eyes
and passed away. Ralph's final word was an ingracious mutter. All right, light
the fire. With some positive action before them, a little of the tension
died. Ralph said no more, did nothing, stood looking down at the ashes around
his feet. Jack was loud and active. He gave orders, sang, whistled, threw
remarks at the silent Ralph, remarks that did not need an answer, and
therefore could not invite a snub. And still Ralph was silent. No one, not even
Jack, would ask him to move. And in the end they had to build the fire three
yards away and in a place not really as convenient. So Ralph asserted his
chieftain ship and could not have chosen a better way if he had thought for days
against his weapon so indefinable and so effective. Jack was powerless and raged
without knowing why. By the time the pile was built, they were on different
sides of a high barrier. When they had dealt with the fire, another crisis
arose. Jack had no means of lighting it.
Then to his surprise, Ralph went to Piggy and took the glasses from him. Not
even Ralph knew how a link between him and Jack had been snapped and fastened elsewhere.
I'll bring him back. I'll come too.
Piggy stood behind him, islanded in a sea of meaningless color, while Ralph
knelt and focused the glossy spot.
Instantly, the fire was a light. Piggy held out his hands and grabbed the
glasses back. Before these fantastically attractive flowers of violet and red and
yellow, unkindness melted away. There became a circle of boys around a
campfire, and even Piggy and Ralph were half drawn in. Soon some of the boys
were rushing down the slope for more wood while Jack hacked the pig. They
tried holding the whole carcass on a steak over the fire, but the steak burnt
more quickly than the pig roasted. In the end, they skewered bits of meat on
branches and held them in the flames, and even then almost as much boy was
roasted as meat. Ralph's mouth watered.
He meant to refuse meat, but his past diet of fruit and nuts with an odd crab
or fish gave him too little resistance.
He accepted a piece of half raw meat, and noded it like a wolf. Piggy spoke,
also dribbling, "Aren't I having none?"
Jack had meant to leave him in doubt as an assertion of power, but Piggy by
advertising his omission made more cruelty necessary. "You didn't hunt."
"No more did Ralph," said Piggy wetly, "Nor Simon," he amplified. "There isn't
more than a haborth of meat in a crab." Ralph stirred uneasily. Simon,
sitting between the twins and Piggy, wiped his mouth and shoved his piece of
meat over the rocks to Piggy, who grabbed it. The twins giggled, and Simon
lowered his face in shame. Then Jack leapt to his feet, slashed off a great
hunk of meat, and flung it down at Simon's feet. "Eat! Damn you!" he glared
at Simon. "Take it!" He spun on his heel, center of a bewildered circle of
boys. He spun on his heel, center of a bewildered circle of boys. "I got you
meat." Numberless and inexpressable frustrations combined to make his rage
elemental and awe inspiring. I painted my face. I stole up. Now you eat all of
you. and I slowly the silence on the mountain top deepened till the click of
the fire and the soft hiss of roasting meat could be heard clearly. Jack looked
round for understanding but found only respect. Ralph stood among the ashes of
the signal fire, his hands full of meat, saying nothing. Then at last Maurice
broke the silence. He changed the subject to the only one that could bring
the majority of them together. Where did you find the pig? Roger pointed down the
unfriendly side. They were there by the sea. Jack, recovering, could not bear to
have his story told. He broke in quickly. We spread round. I crept on
hands and knees. The spears fell out because they hadn't barbs on. The pig
ran away and made an awful noise. It turned back and ran into the circle,
bleeding. All the boys were talking at once, relieved and excited. We closed
in. The first blow had paralyzed its hindquarters. So then the circle could
close in and beat and beat. I cut the pig's throat. The twins, still sharing
their identical grin, jumped up and ran round each other. Then the rest joined
in, making pig dying noises and shouting, "One for his knob. Give him a
four penny one." Then Maurice pretended to be the pig and ran squealing into the
center. And the hunters, circling still, pretended to beat him. As they danced,
they sang, "Killed the pig. Cut her throat. Bash her in." Ralph watched
them, envious and resentful. Not till they flagged and the chant died away did
he speak. I'm calling an assembly. One by one they halted and stood watching
him with the conchk. I'm calling a meeting even if we have to go on into
the dark down on the platform when I blow it now. He turned away and walked
off down the mountain.
Lord of the